Register of the Avenir Gennadievich Efimov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Avenir Gennadievich Efimov papers
1920-1971
2000C21
Hoover Institution Archives
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, orders, and photographs relating to the Russian Civil War. Includes correspondence with B. B. Filimonov.
Efimov, Avenir Gennadievich.
Filimonov, B. B. (Boris Borisovich)
Location of Originals
Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Avenir Gennadievich Efimov was a colonel in the Russian army, the last commander of the remnants of the Izhevsk and Votkinsk divisions of the White army in Siberia. These units were composed of workers of the factories of Izhevsk and Votkinsk in the Ural mountains, who rose against the Soviets in 1918 and joined the White army.
Born on 19 October 1888, Efimov was educated in the Simbirsk Cadet School and graduated from the Nikolaevskoe inzhenernoe uchilishche in 1910, receiving his commission as an officer in the 16th Sapper Battalion quartered in Kazan'.
During the First World War, he completed a course of studies at the General Staff Academy, following which he served at the front in various staff posts until his demobilization on 25 February 1918. Back in Kazan' at the time of the anti-Soviet uprising in the summer of 1918, he joined the People's Army (Narodnaia armiia), in which he served through its unification with the Siberian Army. In February 1919 he was appointed chief of staff of the Izhevsk Rifle Brigade, and when the latter was upgraded to a division, he received command of its cavalry regiment. He was appointed commander of the Izhevsk division in 1920, and presided over its fusion with the fellow votkintsy to form the Izhevsk-Votkinsk brigade, which he commanded until its demobilization.
First in China, and then in San Francisco, California, where he settled, Efimov spent many years collecting documents for a history of the izhevtsy and votkintsy, finally published posthumously as Izhevtsy i votkintsy (Concord, CA, 1975) and now a bibliographic rarity. Efimov died on 25 April 1972 in San Francisco.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains the correspondence of Colonel A. G. Efimov with Boris Borisovich Filimonov, a participant and author of several books on the Russian Civil War in Siberia and the Far East, 1918-1922.
The only writings in the collection are notes and drafts and the printed copy of Efimov's Izhevtsy i votkintsy, a history of these two White army units.
Of particular importance are the documents of the period, which include governmental and army orders (Priamur government and Zemskaia rat') service records, notes and related matter, found in the subject file.
Photographs (Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2:6, consisting of an album entitled "Khabarovskaia ekspeditsiia, 1921-1922," with depictions of the Civil War in the Far East), were not filmed and are not available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920). Armii͡a.
- Correspondence, 1932-1934 (Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 1-3
  Correspondence (and attachments) with Boris Borisovich Filimonov.
- Writings, 1975
  Notes and drafts of chapters of Izhevtsy i votkintsy (Concord, CA, 1975), as well as printed copy.
  - Notes and handwritten drafts (incomplete) (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 4
  - Printed copy (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 5
- Subject File, 1920-1934
  Orders, service records, and other materials relating to the Civil War in Russia, Maritime District, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Primorskaia oblast', Russia. Vremennoe Priamurskoe pravitel'stvo. Orders
    - 1921-1922 (Reel 2)
      Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 6-10
    - 1921-1922 (Reels 2-3)
      Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 1 (Reel 2) and 2: 2 (Reel 3)
    - 1922 (Reel 3)
      Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 3
  - Russia (Territory under White Armies, 1918-1920). Armiia--Officers. Documents relating to the Civil War in the Maritime District, consisting mainly of service records and questionnaires of individual participants, with some correspondence, recommendations, orders, and related matter (Reel 3)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 4-5